http://youtu.be/F9HZfJWdV-A
http://youtu.be/F9HZfJWdV-A khang_vgu
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK, so now that we understand what a register is, and
Vâng, ta đã biết thanh ghi là gì rồi,
the fact that we have instructions that will manipulate these registers,
và có những lệnh để vận hành những thanh ghi này
let's understand what an instruction looks like.
bây giờ hãy tìm hiểu, dòng lệnh là như thế nào?
That is, the format of an instruction.
đây là định dạng của dòng lệnh
An instruction--
một dòng lệnh
we'll take a simple example--
bắt đầu với một ví dụ đơn giản trước
will have an operation.
nó sẽ có cách để thực hiện
For example, I'm saying here I want to move something into a register.
ví dụ, tôi muốn chuyển một thứ gì đó vào một thanh ghi
And in this particular case, I want to move the number 100 into
và trong trường hợp này, tôi muốn chuyển số 100 vào thanh ghi R0
the register R0.
thanh ghi R0
Now, an instruction like this can convey the purpose by commenting it
và dòng lệnh như này có thể cho thấy mục đích, bằng cách ghi chú nó
appropriately.
...
So we put a comment.
ta để một dòng ghi chú ở đây
For example, maybe the purpose of this instruction was to set a table's size.
vi dụ như, mục đích của dòng lệnh này để đặt kích thước của cái bàn
We're using a table of some student records, and this table is going to be
ta chọn một cái bàn, kích thước là 100
So, I put a comment.
ta đặt một ghi chú ở đây
Now, the comment is prefixed by a semicolon.
Và ghi chú được prefixed bằng dấu chấm phẩy ( ; )
Now, typically, an instruction like this may have a label.
một dòng lệnh như này cần có nhãn
So, for example, this is an initialization, so I have a label.
ví dụ, đây là dòng khởi tạo, và ta có một nhãn
So, to review our instruction, then, we say that instruction
và xem lại dòng lệnh, ta thấy
has an opcode, operands--
dòng lệnh này có một mã vận hành, và các toán hạng
This particular instruction required two operands.
dòng lệnh này cần hai toán hạng
There'll be other instructions that might need three operands, four
hoặc có thể dòng lệnh sẽ cần ba, bốn
operands, or even zero operands.
hoặc không toán hạng nào
And then we have a possible comment.
sau đó, ta có một dòng ghi chú
Now, good code should always have copious amounts of comments so that it
đoạn mã tốt thì luôn phải có nhiều dòng ghi chú
has a value for somebody else who's looking at it and easy to understand.
điều đó sẽ giúp người khác dễ hiểu khi đọc
And a label.
và một cái nhãn
Now, we notice that comments and labels are optional, whereas every
như vậy những dòng ghi chú và nhãn thì không bắt buộc,
instruction will have an opcode.
nhưng mỗi dòng lệnh thì cần có một mã vận hành
So, this gives us an idea about what an instruction looks like.
vì vậy nó cho ta biết một lệnh sẽ như thế nào
Let's look at some of the kinds of operations that we perform.
bây giờ là những loại thao tác ta cần thực hiện
The kinds of operations can be broadly classified into four categories.
các thao tác sẽ có 4 loại
The first category is, by far the most important category, is memory access.
loại đầu, quan trọng nhất , là sự truy cập bộ nhớ
So, what we mean by memory access is to load and store information.
sự truy cập bộ nhớ là tải và lưu giữ dữ liệu
So, to load information from.
để tải dữ liệu
For example, we have our registers that are in the
ví dự như, ta có những thanh ghi và nó được đặt trong CPU
CPU, and we have memory.
cấu thành bộ nhớ Memory
So, when we talk about load stored operations, we're talking about
vì vậy, khi nó đến thao tác tải và lưu trữ,
operations to load from memory and to store to memory.
nghĩa là tải từ bộ nhớ và lưu trữ vào bộ nhớ
So, here's an example of a load operation.
vi dụ với thao tác tải
For example, I say LDR R1, [R0].
với LDR R1, [R0]
So, this instruction tells the system that I want to store into register R1.
dòng lệnh này sẽ báo với hệ thống là ta muốn lưu vào thanh ghi R1
Into register R1, I want to store the contents of memory.
vào thanh ghi R1, ta muốn lưu trữ nội dung của bộ nhớ
So there's an address here.
có một địa chỉ ở đây
We're saying that it holds an address.
nghĩa là nó sẽ giữ một địa chỉ
Go to that location and access, fetch the contents of that address, and put
là hãy đến vị trí đó, truy cập nội dung của địa chỉ
it in register R1.
và đặt nó vào thanh ghi R1
So, that's a memory access instruction.
và đó là lệnh cho thao tác truy cập bộ nhớ
The second instruction, obviously we want to do some work on these things
dòng lệnh thứ hai ta sẽ làm những thao tác tiếp theo
that we bring into registers.
ta đưa vào những thanh ghi
So, the second class of operations are arithmetic and logic operations.
và thao tác thứ hai la phép toán số học và luận lý (logic)
Arithmetic and logic operations could be something as simple as add,
các phép toán này có thẻ là
subtract, and arithmetic operations, add, subtract, multiply, and so on.
cộng, trừ, nhân, chia,...
Multiply and divide.
....
Or they can be logical operations like performing an and operation,
hoặc có thể là phép toán luận lý như phép toán AND
performing a shift operation.
phép toán dịch
Again, here's a simple example of an add operation.
đây là ví dụ vè thêm phép toán
So, ADD R1, R3, R7.
cộng R1, R3, R7
So this instruction is telling us to take the contents of R7 and R3 and add
lệnh này nói rằng, lấy nội dung của R7 và R3
them together and put the result in R1.
cộng nó lại và đặt vào R1
Here's a third class of operations.
tiếp đến là loại thao tác thử ba
These are control operations.
là thao tác điều khiển
Control operations are operations that change the flow of code.
nghĩa là những thao tác thay đổi "dòng chảy của mã"
What we mean by change the flow of code is, we sometimes, in our program
"dòng chảy của mã" ở đây là, trong chương trình
will branch from one location to another location, or we may call a
chương trình sẽ rẽ nhánh từ vị trí này tới vị trí khác
subroutine.
đó là chương trình con
Here's a simple example of a flow instruction, a control instruction.
đây là một ví dụ về lệnh điều khiển
A branch equal to a label, which is isEqual.
một nhánh thì tương đương với một nhãn, nó là isEqual
So, what this is saying is, if the Z bit is equal to 1, which is how we
ở đây nói là, nếu Z bit bằng với 1,
indicate that the two things are equal, the Z bit is equal to 1, then
ở đây, cách ta định nghĩa 2 cái bằng nhau
branch to a label, which is a label like that.
nhãn sẽ như thế này
Branch to a label, which is isEqual.
...
The last class of operations are special instructions.
loại thao tác cuối cùng là những lệnh  đặc biệt
These could be instructions that don't have an equivalent, they're not merely
những lệnh này thì không có lệnh tương đương
access, they're not logic operations, but they have a special purpose.
chúng không phải các phép toán luận lý, nhưng chúng có mục đích đặc biệt
So these special instructions, for example, are things like to turn off
những lệnh đặc biệt này, ví dụ như đóng hoặc khởi động sự ngắt (interrupt)
interrupts, to disable or enable interrupts.
...
So here's an example of a special instruction.
đây là ví dụ của một lệnh đặc biệt
This is the CPSIE with an operand I, which tells the system to enable
đây là CPSIE với một toán hạng I,
interrupts.
nó thông báo cho hệ thống, để khởi động interrupt
The E here is for enable.
E ở đây là để khởi động
So there's an equivalent, which is CPSID, which tells the system to
và cũng có một lệnh tương tự, là CPSID,
disable interrupts.
để thông báo hệ thống đóng (interrupt)